You weren't followed?
没被跟踪吧？
No.
没
Better come in.
快请进
Trust no one, Jim.
吉姆，谁都别信
Especially not in the mainstream.
尤其是那些要人
请坐
Sit down.
我知道你仍有一个匈牙利身份可用
I understand you still have one Hungarian identity running?
是的
I do.
I want you to go to Budapest.
我想派你去布达佩斯（匈牙利首都）
This is not above board.
秘密行动
Nobody else knows.
他人不知
他们在找我，吉姆小子
They're after my head, Jim boy.
Do you understand?
你明白吗？
我听小道消息说
I have had an offer of service.
一位匈牙利将军要来访
A Hungarian general wants to come over.
I would like you to meet him.
我想让你会会他
他有我要的情报，吉姆
He has some information that I need, Jim.
What information?
什么情报？
重要机密
Treasure.
He has the name of the mole...
他知道“地鼠”的名字…
一个俄国佬在英国情报部门安插的内鬼…
the Russians have planted in the British intelligence service...
right at the top of the Circus.
就在“圆场”的高层中
There's a rotten apple, Jim.
有个内鬼，吉姆
我们得把他挖出来
We have to find it.
还有匈牙利炖肉，你尝过吧？
是的，我尝过
味道很棒，比炖牛肉强多了，但你现在在布达佩斯吃不到
为什么？
所有的猪都到莫斯科去了
我什么时候能见上你的朋友？
我会带你去见他的，不吃点么？
容我失陪一会？
站住！
Stop!
别开枪！
谁让你开枪的？谁他妈让你开枪的？
该死的业余匈牙利杀手！我要留活口！
我要留活口！
英国秘密情报局首领
参考文献：c/1234   日期：1973年11月14日
你们愿为我作证吗？
Would you witness this for me?
I wish I could done more, Control.
很遗憾我没能做什么，老总
You did all you could, Percy.
你已经尽力了，珀西
Well, a man should know when to leave the party.
人应该懂得适时而退
史迈利呢？
What about Smiley?
Smiley is leaving with me.
史迈利随我一起离开
You little prick, Esterhase.
你这蠢货，伊斯特哈斯
片名：锅匠 裁缝 士兵 间谍
Gentlemen, shall we start?
先生们，我们开始吧？
珀西先生，副局长拉康在等您
Under Secretary Lacon is ready for you, Sir Percy.
财政部不解
The Treasury don't understand.
情报部门为何不为经费增加的问题
Why can't the intelligence service simply put in a request
提交一个正式的申请呢
for a general increase in funding
那样不就可以支撑你们的专项行动了吗？
and then you account for the spend on your special operation?
Operation Witchcraft needs to remain secret.
“巫术行动”需要保密
It's a fiefdom of its own.
- 有自治权限   - 这也是困扰我们的原因
Yes, that's what's worrying us.
整件事难以解释，不是吗？
The whole thing's very unaccountable, isn't it?
And this London house that nobody knows the address of,
没人知道这间伦敦宅子在哪儿
is that really necessary?
有这个必要吗？
Now more than ever. We need to protect our Soviet source.
比起从前，现在更需要保护我们的苏联信源
So where do you propose we meet? In a cafe?
那你认为我们该在哪接头？咖啡馆？
房租和费率都翻了倍
The rent and rates on this house have doubled.
我们在核弹头上花了数百万
We spent millions on nuclear warheads.
却不能为一间房子申请几千块
We're asking for a few thousand for a house.
我在想卡拉在克里姆林宫（苏联）的财政上
I wonder if Karla has the same problem
是否也遇到相同的问题
with the Treasury at the Kremlin.
听着，没人低估
Look, nobody underestimates
你们工作的重要性
the importance of the job you chaps are doing.
可去年在布达佩斯发生的事
But what happened in Budapest last year,
着实让人心有余悸
that was a disaster.
恕我直言，先生
With respect, sir,
牺牲的不是您的手下，对吧？
it wasn't one of your civil servants that got killed, was it?
Now this isn't about soldiers in trenches any more.
战壕士兵冲锋的时候已经过去了
- 如今是我们首当其冲…   - 罗伊！
- We're the front line now... - Roy!
For 25 years we've been the
过去的25年里，我们是唯一坚持与他们和卡拉
only thing standing between them and Karla
还有莫斯科跟该死的第三次世界大战抗衡的力量
and Moscow and the third bloody world war.
听着，部长大人对你们目前工作的进展表示满意
Look, the Minister's very pleased with your progress so far.
He's less pleased, though,
但对于跟我们美国同盟的进展
他就不太满意了
with the lack of progress with our American cousins.
You see,
你知道
in their eyes,
在他们眼中
你们仍是条漏水的船
you're still a leaky ship.
Yes?
什么事？
Someone on the line for you, sir. Seems urgent.
有人找您，先生，好像很急
All right, well put him through.
好的，接通吧
- 你好？   - 是副局长拉康吗？
- Hello? - Is this Under Secretary Lacon?
正是
Yes.
My name's Ricki Tarr.
我叫里基•塔尔
- What do you want? - I need to meet you.
- 有事吗？   - 我想见您
如果您要核实我的身份，可以找我“圆场”的上司
If you need to confirm who I am,
you can talk to my boss at the Circus,
Peter Guillam.
彼得•吉勒姆
But only Guillam, no one else.
只有他知道我
允许你骑车进来吗？
You got clearance for that?
Well, I'm not bloody chaining it up outside.
我才不会傻得把它锁在外面呢
Mind you, no better off in
友情提醒，和里面这些狠角儿放一起相对安全
here with this bunch of bloody cut-throats.
他们连你嘴里的消息都挖的出来
They'd have the gold out of your teeth.
我得赶在布兰德之前看一眼新来的姑娘
Thought I'd pop in and catch a
glimpse of the new girl before Bland gets to her.
是啊，金发女郎贝琳达
Ah, yes. Belinda the blonde.
- Has he seen her yet? - Of course he has.
- 他见过她没？   - 肯定见过
Came down first thing this morning.
今早第一件事就是看她
贝琳达
Belinda.
- 我是彼得•吉勒姆   - 你好啊，彼得，我是奥利弗
Peter Guillam.
Hello, Peter, this is Oliver.
想问问你…
Just ringing to find out...
这么说是温斯顿•丘吉尔救了你一命，伊迪
So Winston Churchill saved your life, Edie.
当时我在厨房备好了晚餐
I was working in the kitchen, getting dinner ready.
他迟到了
And he was late, you see.
- During a raid? - During a raid, you see.
- 突袭的时候？   - 是的
他问，你为什么不在那个避难所？
He said, "Why aren't you in that shelter?"
- 你不也不在么？   - 因为我…
- Why weren't you? - Well, because...
I was sorry to hear about Control, Mr. Smiley.
很遗憾听到老总的死讯，史迈利先生
He said Tarr called him from a phone box.
他说塔尔在电话亭给他致电
He said there's a mole,
他说有“地鼠”
right at the top of the Circus,
就在“圆场”的高层里
that he's been there for years.
已潜伏多年
It does mean
那就是说
you're rather well placed to look into this matter for us now,
你最好给我们立即查清楚原委
是不？
doesn't it?
Outside the family.
把他清除出去
I'm retired, Oliver.
我已经退休了，奥利弗
You fired me.
你解雇了我
The thing is,
实际上
some time ago before Control died,
老总死前
曾来找我，暗示我说
he came to me with a similar suggestion.
That there is a mole.
有“地鼠”
He never mentioned his suspicions to you?
他没对你讲过他的怀疑么？
No.
没有
Oh, I just thought that as you were his man, so to speak...
噢，我以为你是他的心腹，会跟你讲…
你怎么跟他说的？
What did you say to him?
我想恐怕是他的妄想症在作祟
I'm afraid I thought his
paranoia had rather gotten the better of him
他想推倒重来
and he was going to pull his whole house down.
That bloody mess in Budapest.
还有布达佩斯的惨剧
不可否认，乔治
Damn it, George.
如今是你的时代
It's your generation, your legacy.
I would have thought,
我本以为若有蹊跷，你会愿意…
if there's any truth in it, you'd want to...
I'll keep Peter.
我要彼得
还有一个政治保安处退下来的人，孟德尔
And there's a retired Special Branch man, Mendel.
I should like to have him.
我要他
提起来
Lift up.
And quickly down again.
再赶紧关好
There's a place I know, sir.
先生，我知道一个利物浦大街附近的小旅馆
A little hotel near Liverpool Street.
请小心点，乔治王时代的
Be careful with it. Please. It's Georgian.
我朋友想要安静工作，波普格雷姆夫人
My friend wants peace and quiet
in order to work, Mrs. Pope Graham.
不要打搅他
No disturbances.
她真名只是格雷姆
Her real name is just Graham.
Added the Pope for a touch of class.
加上波普以表等级
Peter, did you get the keys to Control's flat?
彼得，你有老总住处的钥匙吗？
And did those feet in ancient time
walk upon England's mountains green?
噢！
George!
乔治！
George, get in here!
乔治快来
George.
乔治
坐下
Sit down.
看看这荒谬的文件
Take a look at this nonsense.
Report by Soviet high command
苏联最高指挥部的
关于他们近期于黑海的海军演练的报告
on their recent naval exercises in the Black Sea.
Just what the admiralty has been begging us
正是海军部求咱们
for some information on.
弄的情报
- Where did you get this? - I didn't.
- 哪儿得到的？   - 不是我
珀西和他的小团队搞到的
Percy and his little cabal walked in with it.
- 听着，老总…   - 闭嘴
- Look, Control... - Shut up.
Style appalling.
文体骇人
Patently a fabrication from beginning to end.
明显从头到尾都是伪造的
- 也有可能是真的   - 如果是真的，那可价值连城
Just could be the real thing.
Well, if it's genuine, it's gold dust.
不过它的时事性令人生疑
But its topicality makes it suspect.
史迈利怀疑，珀西
Smiley is suspicious, Percy.
Where did it come from? What's the access?
哪儿来的？什么渠道？
我的一个新的秘密线人
A new secret source of mine.
But how could he possibly have access?
可他又怎么有渠道？
他可以搞到决策层的高级机密
He has access to the most sensitive levels of policy-making.
我们命名这个行动为“巫术”
We've named the operation Witchcraft.
珀西和他的伙伴们越过咱们了，史迈利
Oh, Percy and his pals bypassed us, Smiley.
直接找部长去了
Gone straight to the minister.
Percy has been allowed to keep the identity of his new friend
允许珀西对他新朋友的身份
绝对保密
top secret.
The minister agrees too many secrets are blown around here.
部长也认同这里太多的机密被泄露了
Too much failure, too many scandals.
不胜枚举的失败，接连不断的丑闻
-有用的情报少得可怜   - 老总，珀西说到点子上了
Too little solid intelligence.
Percy does have a point, Control.
我们应该反共，而不是内讧
We should be fighting Communism, not each other.
与此同时，我们信誉扫地，损兵折将
Meanwhile we're losing our reputation, our partners.
Your bloody Yanks!
你们该死的美国佬！
我们受够了！得改革了
We've had enough! There's going to be changes.
是时候决定是固步自封还是开创未来了
We need to decide if want
to be part of the past or part of the future.
当年我就不该把你带来
I should have left you where I found you.
- 听着！   - 老总…
- Look! - Control...
Out, all of you!
滚，都给我滚出去！
如果“巫术”是真的…
If Witchcraft is genuine...
没有什么是真的
Nothing is genuine any more.
George...
乔治…
要我把这些东西带到旅馆吗？
Do you want me to get this stuff over to the hotel?
Thank you. Uh, anywhere will do.
谢谢，随便放
- 彼得？   - 嗯？
Peter?
我要你替我办点事
I need you to do something for me.
[卡拉]
I'd like you to go to the Circus.
你去“圆场”
在值班岗那儿的橱柜里
In the cabinet at the duty officers' station
are records of staff recently retired.
有最近退休人员的记录
拍成照片给我
I'd like photographs of them
and of the diagram of the
还有珀西•阿勒莱恩为“圆场”设计的重组表
Circus's reorganisation under Percy Alleline,
和所有行动基金的支付清单
along with a list of all payments made from the Reptile fund.
Help you with anything, Bill?
- 比尔，什么事？   - 我在找“陛下”
I was just looking for his Majesty.
他到城墙散步去了
Well, he's out walking the battlements.
哦
- 听说你受伤了，彼得？   - 开抽屉的时候夹了手
Heard you had an accident, Peter.
Yeah, I cut my hand open on a drawer.
When are you going to get some new furniture up here?
你什么时候去置办些新家具？
I'll have a word with Esterhase.
我会跟伊斯特哈斯说的，让顶楼的优先考虑这事
We'll make it a priority on the top floor.
- 你去哪儿？   - 吃午饭
- Where are you off to? - Lunch.
一起？
Want some company?
根据人事档案
According to the personnel files,
有七个到了退休年龄
seven were due for retirement anyway.
其他四个也没有太明显的疑点
Another four don't seem particularly mysterious.
杰瑞•韦斯特比于12月4日被解雇
Jerry Westerby was dismissed December 4.
Connie Sachs retired November 28.
康妮•萨克斯于11月28日退休
That's just two weeks after you and Control were forced out.
那是在你和老总被挤走后的两周里发生的
- Return to Oxford, please. - That's 1.15.
- 回牛津   - 1点15的车
珀西向来反对
Percy has always resisted any proposal
of a wider exploitation of Witchcraft's intelligence.
广泛利用“巫术”情报的提议
Drop the bloody jargon, Lacon.
别跟我扯行话，拉康
I've refused to share
我至今未跟同盟们分享过“巫术”，部长大人
Witchcraft with our allies so far, Minister.
吝啬的家伙
Greedy boy.
毋庸置疑我正在向目标慢慢靠拢
My goal has been to establish its track record beyond all doubt.
我觉得是时候携手我们的美国盟友了
I think the time has come
to approach our American brothers-in-arms.
- 他们会拉我们入伙么？   - 我不要一次性交易
Will they take us back into bed?
I'm not interested in a one-off trade.
I want on-going access to American intelligence.
我要长期的美国情报
你觉得我们能办到？
You think we can get it?
只要有“巫术”，我们可以得到任何想要的
With Witchcraft on our side,
we can get anything we bloody well want.
Fine.
好吧
Carry on.
继续下去
谢谢
Thank you.
我要打败你…
And I strike thee down...
Oh, I, uh...
哦，我…
想都别想，医生有吩咐
Not supposed to. Doctor's orders.
Wicked, wicked George.
坏坏的乔治
我不知道你怎么想的，乔治
I don't know about you, George,
but I feel seriously under-fucked.
但我像是被肏了一样
我听说安又弃你而去了
I heard Ann left you again.
她配不上你，乔治，连你一根头发都配不上
She doesn't deserve you, George, not one hair on your head.
You left the Circus shortly after I retired.
我退休不久，你也离开了“圆场”
我是被开除的
I didn't leave. I was dismissed.
被开除的垃圾，和你一样
Chucked out on the rubbish heap, like you.
Why?
为什么？
波利亚科夫
Polyakov.
Do you remember him?'
还记得他吗？
From the Soviet Embassy?'
苏联大使馆的那位？
Alexsey Polyakov, cultural attach here in London.
阿联克斯•波利亚科夫，以文化交流为由常驻伦敦
15年前他来到这里，我要求对其清查
When he arrived here 15 years ago,
I requested he be checked out.
可他记录清白，为人谨慎
He was graded whiter than white. Didn't put a foot wrong.
但你不这么认为？
But you disagreed?'
There's a story you must have heard
你肯定听闻过这个传说
that Karla has set up a secret cell.
卡拉设立了个秘密单元
所有成员都是以前军人
The personnel are all ex-military,
trained to handle deep-penetration agents, moles.
训练有素地掌控着资深间谍和“地鼠”们
传说是不绝的，康妮
There are always stories, Connie.
万一这个传说是真的呢？
But what if this story was true?
有一晚在调查中我发现了些东西，乔治
One night in research I saw something, George.
我们的朋友波利亚科夫在柏林五一大阅兵中
There was our friend Polyakov at a May day parade in Berlin
receiving a salute.
受了一个军礼
为什么要向一个文化专员敬礼？
Why would you salute a cultural attach?
显然，除非他是个退伍军人
Exactly. Unless he was a war veteran himself'.
若真如此，为何要隐瞒真相？
And if he was, why hide the fact?
你怎么做的？
What did you do?
我直接去找托比•伊斯特哈斯和珀西•阿勒莱恩
I went straight to Esterhase and Alleline.
看
Here.
如果我没弄错的话，波利亚科夫是卡拉训练的人
Polyakov is a Karla-trained hood if ever I saw one.
If he's here, it must be because he's running a mole.
他若在这儿，说明他安插了“地鼠”于此
You're to leave Polyakov alone.
你不要管波利亚科夫
你太纠缠他了
You're becoming obsessed with him.
- 不要越俎代庖   - 太荒唐了
You're losing your sense of proportion,Connie.
But that's ridiculous.
也许是时候让你回到现实的世界了
Perhaps it's time you went out into the real world.
阿联克斯·波利亚科夫
What does it matter? Old Circus is gone anyway.
走就走，反正从前的“圆场”已经逝去了
Here we are.
看看这些
我们那时的日子
The nursery in our day.
吉姆•普里多
Jim Prideaux.
And Bill Haydon. Together, of course.
当然还有比尔•海顿，一起
The inseparables.
形影不离的一对
还有老总的独照
There's Control himself.
我的伙伴们
All my boys.
我的好战友
All my lovely boys.
那时真美妙，乔治
That was a good time, George.
It was the war, Connie.
战争使然，康妮
A real war.
真正的战争
英国人可以引以为豪
Englishmen could be proud then.
我还是对的，是吧？
So I was right, then?
About Polyakov.
至少关于波利亚科夫
确有“地鼠”
There is a mole.
若真如此，请勿回来，我想把记忆定格在你们都美好的时候
If it's bad, don't come back.
I want to remember you all as you were.
珀西？珀西，你调的这汤？
Percy? Percy, did you mix this?
是，是我调的
Aye, I did so.
You Calvinistic, penny-pinching Scot.
你这个小气的没救的苏格兰人
Can you nae learn to take a bloody order?
你这种外行就不能按食谱来做吗？
谁也不能乱改食谱！
Nobody tampers with the recipe!
- 我就是按着食谱来的啊   - 别说了
- I followed the recipe. - Come on.
跟猴尿似的玩意儿，让人怎么下咽
It'll take us five hours to get drunk on this monkey's piss.
He's not the first
- He's the second best secret agent - Merry Christmas.
圣诞快乐
In the whole wide world
He's not number one
But not the worst
He's just the second best secret agent
In the whole wide world
He's every bit
As good as what's-his-name
With a dame
Any dame
And all those bullet holes are in his vest
To prove you work a little harder
When you're second best... ?
Courtesy of Mrs. P.
- 皮夫人问好   - 嗯？
You been up all night?
你通宵了？
是的
Yes.
这是什么？
What's this?
去行动基金要的1000块现金
To a Mr. Ellis.
给一个叫埃尔斯的先生
It was one of Jim Prideaux's work names.
吉姆•普里多的一个工作化名
Prideaux was killed in Hungary a year ago.
普里多一年前于匈牙利遇害
October 21.
10月21日
那为何还有人于两个月后给他1000块？
I wonder where he is then, sir.
我在想他后来到哪去了，先生
Settle down now.
安静
- 发下去   - 是，先生
- Hand those out. - Sir.
What is it? The Hunchback of Notre-Dame?
这是什么？巴黎圣母院的敲钟人？
钟，钟！
The bells, the bells!
噢！
出来吧
Come here.
- What's your name? - Roach. Bill Roach, sir.
- 叫什么名字？   - 罗奇，比尔•罗奇
- I'm a new boy. - New arrival, eh?
- 我是新生   - 新来的哦？
- 怎么回事？   - 我父亲和母亲
- What's the story? - My mother and father.
My father left, so...
我父亲走了，所以…
嗯
Bill.
比尔（账单）
The unpaid Bill.
未付账的账单
- Anyone ever call you that? - No, sir.
- 有人那么叫你吗？   - 没有，先生
我认识很多叫比尔的人
Known a lot of Bills in my time.
他们都是好人
They've all been good 'uns.
What are you good at?
你擅长什么？
Nothing, sir.
一无所长，先生
You're a good watcher, though, eh?
但你擅于观察，对吗？
我们孤独者都如此
Us loners always are.
Best watcher in the unit, Bill Roach is, I'll bet.
一旦你带上眼镜，我打赌，比尔•罗奇
- Long as he's got his specs on. Right? - Yes, sir.
- 你一定是班上最好的观察者，对吗？   - 是的，先生
很好，非常好
This is good, very good.
你好，里基
Hello, Ricki.
你疏忽了门上的楔子
You've missed the wedge.
你去哪了，里基？
Where have you been, Ricki?
他们追杀我
They're going to kill me.
- Who is? - Your lot.
- 谁？   - 你们的人
或许他们的人，无论谁逮到，我都得死
Or their lot. Whoever gets me first.
I'm innocent.
我是清白的
Within reason.
情有可原
你来这多久了？
How long have you been here?
Sorry, I've run out of places now.
对不起，我走投无路
I needed to see you.
我需要见你
Why?
为什么？
There's a woman.
有一个女人
I need you to trade for her.
我需要你去交易帮我把她从卡拉那弄回来
I need you to get her back off Karla.
什么女人？
A woman?
Her name's Irina.
她叫依瑞娜
去年十一月
This was last November.
吉勒姆先生派我去伊斯坦布尔调查一个俄贸代表
Mr. Guillam sent me to
Istanbul to check out a Russian trade delegate
who might be persuaded to defect.
这人有被说服投靠我方的可能
- Tufty Thesinger, resident. - Yeah.
- 叫塔夫帝•赛森哲，驻外政治代表   - 就是他
- 你好，里基   - 旅程还行吧，伙计？
- Hiya, Ricki. - All right, mate?
- Did you know him? - No, never met him.
- 你认识他？   - 不，没见过
那人有点嗜酒
Bit of a drinker.
宿醉的鬼样
Hangover from hell.
Bit of a fucking idiot.
挺白痴的
Apparently this Russian, name of Boris,
很明显这个叫鲍里斯的俄国人
was spending high and wide in the nightclubs.
混迹于各个夜店，浪荡挥霍
So you were sent to persuade this Boris?
你就是来游说这个鲍里斯的？
Yeah. He was your typical Russian.
是的，他就是典型的俄国人
Trade delegation by day, out boozing every night.
天亮贸易谈判，夜晚寻欢作乐
Didn't seem to sleep.
乐此不疲
Tufty was worn out from following him around.
这可把跟踪他的塔夫帝给熬倒了
I think it's going to be a long night, son.
漫漫长夜啊，孩子
His favourite haunt was this club in Taksim.
他常出没于塔克西姆广场的一个夜总会
地下室有个“天上人间”，水手和游客常常光顾
It had a hellhole in the
basement where the sailors and the tourists went.
Anyway, I took one look at him and I knew I'd wasted a journey.
总之，我看他一眼就知道这趟旅途泡汤了
Boris was no delegate.
鲍里斯不是什么代表
What delegate bothers to play drunker than he really is?
酒鬼代表何必去扮一个酒鬼？
You get to recognise your own, don't you, Mr. Smiley?
这得靠自己去识别，不是吗，史迈利先生？
鲍里斯是莫斯科“中心”
And Boris was a hood.
Moscow Centre trained.
训练出来的爪牙
Someone is waiting
I mean just for you
Spinning wheel
Keep on spinning through, drop all your troubles...
I guessed he was waiting for a connect.
我猜他在等接头
Working a letterbox, maybe.
也可能是在等消息
Or trailing his coat and
或者挑起事端，从像我这样心怀鬼胎的人身上寻找机遇
looking for a pass from some mug like me.
所以次夜我去了趟进出口机构
So the second night I went to the import/export outfit
that Tufty had set up with a cipher room hidden in the back.
塔夫帝在深处设了间密室
I cabled "No sale" to Mr. Guillam.
我发送了“不外售”的电报给吉勒姆先生
就那样
And that was that.
You were due to fly home the next day.
次日你本该飞回来
是的
Yes.
But you didn't.
但你没有
Boris had a wife.
鲍里斯有一个老婆
Common-law.
法律上的妻子
Apparently she was a member of the delegation in her own right.
显然她也是有一席之地的代表团成员
You once told me to trust my instincts about women, Mr. Smiley.
史迈利先生，您曾教导我相信对女人的直觉
Well, my instincts told me this woman had some treasure.
我的直觉告诉我，这个女人有料
When Boris went out for the night,
那晚当鲍里斯出去后，我告诉自己该去旅馆找她
I found myself going into her hotel.
所以你放弃跟踪鲍里斯
So you dropped Boris.
I know. It was breaking protocol.
我知道我坏了规矩
But I was acting on my own initiative, as it were.
但可以说是我不由自主的在行动
Your man's a bit of a bastard, isn't he?
你男人真混蛋，不是吗？
我只想来确认下你没啥大碍，行吗？
I just wanted to make sure you were all right, OK?
So you didn't come home?
所以你没有回来？
I would have.
本该回的
Boris was a dead end, but...
最后鲍里斯死了，可是…
唔…
I could...
我可以…
I could sense something in her.
我可以感受到她的内心的有某种
A secret.
秘密
And how did you intend to get this secret out of her?
那你打算怎么从她那弄到这个秘密？
我装成一个叫迈克尔•钱奇的商人
I played this businessman, Michael Trench.
Holiday romance.
共度浪漫假日
I thought I'd take my time with it.
我心想不着急
我知道你的真实身份
I know who you are.
I want to talk to your boss.
我要跟你的上司谈话
Control.
老总
I have something to trade.
我有东西要交易
Something big.
很重要
I want a new life in the West.
我想在西部重新生活
That's the deal.
这就是我的要求
You tell them.
你转告他们
Look, you can't expect them to jump at every offer of service.
听着，别指望他们对任何情报都欣然接受
If you won't tell me more, there is nothing I can do.
如果你不能提供更多的情报，我也无能为力
If I tell you everything,
若我全盘托出
I'm putting my life in your hands.
那我就把命交到你们的手里了
And the lives of other people.
还有其他人的命
于是她就告诉了我她要交换的
So she told me what she had to trade.
Her secret.
秘密
我意思是
I mean,
the mother of all secrets.
所有秘密的母体
I told her I'd alert the Circus.
我告诉她我会通知“圆场”的
She made me promise I
她要我保证不能向伦敦透露任何细节
wouldn't give any of the details to London.
- And you agreed? - Yes.
- 你同意了   - 是的
I mean it was...
我意思…
I couldn't believe I'd got hold of something this big.
我都不敢相信我搜集到了这么大的情报
I went back to the import/export,
我回到进出口机构
sent the message to the Circus,
给“圆场”发了封“最高紧急级别”的电报
graded, "Flash, highest priority",
just that I had a Moscow-trained hood wanting to defect.
说我有一个想叛变的莫斯科爪牙
你怎么还没走，伦敦当局找上我了
You're supposed to have gone. London stations have been on to me.
Want to know what the hell you're doing.
想知道你到底在搞什么鬼
Fuck off.
滚开
Anything else, Ricki?
还有吗，里基？
I know what I am to the Circus.
我知道对于“圆场”，我只是一名头皮猎人（变异的反派漫画人物）
I'm one of the scalp-hunters,
someone that you can hand your dirty little jobs to.
那种干些微不足道的脏活累活的人
I just...
我只是…
I just wanted to bring this one in myself.
这次我想亲手上交情报
我理解你的感受
Well, I understand how you felt.
You wanted to do something.
你想办点大事
我说她有关系到“圆场”安危的
I said that she claimed to have information
vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
重要情报
Anything more?
还有吗？
I said that she had information concerning a double agent.
我还说她的情报涉及到双重间谍
Look, I just wanted to get the proper attention. And I'd...
听着，我只想引起足够的重视，而且…
I told them this was the reason why I had not come home.
我告诉他们这就是我当时没有回来的原因
并不是我叛变了什么的
It wasn't that I'd defected or anything.
- What did you do then? - I waited for a reply.
- 你之后怎么做的？   - 我等待回复
I hung around for hours. I heard the Imsak call to prayer.
我来回走了几个小时，听着自己祷告
So what's that? That's about 3.30 in the morning.
之后，凌晨3点半左右吧
Then the message comes through.
电报来了
"We read you".
“已读”
That was all they sent. Nothing.
仅此，别无他言
It didn't make sense. It was like they were stalling'.
讲不通啊，他们就像在拖延时间
Then what happened?
然后呢？
Then, all of a sudden...
突然…
the Russians begin to move.
俄国佬开始行动了
It was nice work. I couldn't have done it better myself.
手法漂亮，令我望尘莫及
这信息很明了，我得警告她
The message was quite clear. I needed to warn her.
快点，快点
Come on, come on, come on.
I've looked for everywhere.
我在机场找不到她
I couldn't find her at the airport.
I even looked through all the flight lists and...
我几乎查看了所有的班次…
I headed down to the harbour.
还去了港口
他们把她押到了去敖德萨(俄罗斯港市)的船上
They put her on a ship to Odessa.
That's all I know.
我只知道这么多
我…
I've...
I've done a lot of things in my life, Mr. Smiley, but...
我此生做了很多事情，史迈利先生，可…
I just... I can't stop thinking about her.
她却让我难以忘怀
She wasn't even my type.
她甚至不是我喜欢的类型
I've got to get her out. I owe her that.
我得把她弄出来，我欠她的
Karla will be looking for you.
卡拉会找你的
Everybody's looking for me.
人人都在找我
此地不宜久留
You can't stay here.
It isn't safe.
不安全
I said, "You may fuck me
我说：“你可以对我不屑，但早上见到我你还得管我叫 ‘先生’”
but you'll call me "Sir" in the morning".
OK.
好了，只是想让你知道
Just need to let you know.
有人上周用我们的逃亡护照飞往巴黎
Someone flew into Paris
last week on one of our escaped passports.
- 然后呢？   - 此人就是里基•塔尔
- And? - It was Ricki Tarr.
Why are you telling me?
跟我说做什么？
- 可能是巧合吧…   - 你这狠毒的侏儒
- It could be coincidence... - You are a poisoned dwarf.
Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty
你为何不滚回你的陛下那？
and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret?
休想将我卷入鸿门宴
伊斯特哈斯先生：“可能是巧合，不过…”
Mr. Esterhase: "It could be coincidence but"...
海顿先生打断
Mr. Haydon interrupting.
"You really are a poisoned dwarf, Toby.
“你真是个狠毒的侏儒，托比”
"Why don't you fuck off to his Majesty
你为何不滚回你的陛下那？
休想将我卷入鸿门宴
"and stop trying to involve me in your cabaret?"
You look tired.
你看起来很疲惫
没睡好
I didn't sleep well.
You're going to do something for me, Peter.
彼得，为我做点事
I need the duty officer's log book for last November.
我需要去年11月值班处的登记日志
I'm going to have to send you up a floor into the lions' den.
我不得不把你送进楼上的虎穴
你若被逮
If you're caught,
you can't mention me.
不能提我
我很抱歉，你得只身前往
I'm sorry, but you're alone.
- 去年11月的？   - 嗯
- Last November? - Hm.
Mr. Guillam!
吉勒姆先生！
谢谢你，布莱恩特
Bryant.
家人还好吧？
How's the family?
Fine. Need to go up to the registry today.
挺好的，我今天要上登记处去
OK, sir.
好的
你会需要一个黄色便条，先生
Now you'll need a yellow one for the bag, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
- 早安，吉勒姆先生   - 早，阿尔文
Good morning, Mr. Guillam.
Morning, Alwyn.
- Want me to look after that for you? - Thank you.
- 需要我帮您照看吗？   - 谢谢
I'll need your chit, Mr. Guillam.
需要您的便条，吉勒姆先生
Dolphin will kill me if I don't. New rules.
如果您不留的话我会很为难，上面的新规定
So, chit me.
请便
Thanks.
谢谢
- Sal, lovely surprise. - Peter.
- 桑儿，很高兴见到你   - 彼得
- What are you up to this weekend? - Oh, you know.
- 周末做什么去？   - 你知道的
Visiting aunts.
拜访七大姑八大姨
I'll bet.
我猜就是
D走廊
Corridor D.
中途右侧88号
The two eights are halfway on your right.
The three ones are next alcove down.
111号在下一个凹室
多谢
Thanks.
Here's a request from Libby Barr from Bromley
for "Mr. Wu's A Window Cleaner Now".
Take it away, George.
Hello. Archive, Alwyn speaking.
你好，档案部，我是阿尔文，请讲
Can I speak to Mr. Guillam, please?
我找吉勒姆
I'm his car mechanic.
我是他的修车工
Well, I'll just see if he's available. Hold on, please.
我去看看他是否有空，请稍等
Mr. Wu, what shall I do?
- Oh, Christ! - Telephone, sir.
- 天哪！   - 有你电话，先生
- Who is it? - Outside line, sir. Someone rough.
- 什么人？   - 外线，一个大老粗
Sir?
先生？
- 喂？   - 您的变速箱崩了，先生
- Hello? - Your gearbox is bust, sir.
该死，你难道不会修吗？
Damn it, can't you fix the bloody thing?
Can't be done, sir.
不好修
Afraid you're gonna need a new gearbox.
恐怕得换了
Well, phone the main dealership first. Have you got their number?
先打给主经销商，有他们电话吗？
No.
没有
Hang on. Alwyn!
等下，阿尔文！
- Alwyn. - Sir?
- 阿尔文   - 什么事？
把我的包给我，可以吗？
Get me my bag, will you?
- But... - Just for a second.
- 可…   - 就一下
Thank you.
谢谢
Hang on.
等下
- Hello? - I'm listening.
- 在吗？   - 我在听
- Yes. 9-4-6-0-3-3-5. - Be right on it, sir.
- 记住了，先生
Thank you.
谢谢
彼得•吉勒姆
Peter Guillam.
Could we see you, please?
我们能见见你吗？
Percy would like quite an urgent word with you.
珀西有急话要对你讲
If you can come now to the fifth floor that would be so kind.
如果你现在能去趟五楼，就最好不过了
Yes, of course.
好的
Throw that into the lift for me.
帮我扔到电梯
Send it to the second floor, save me filling out bloody chits.
送到二楼，省的我去填那些烦人的单子
Will do, sir.
放心，先生
So what have you been getting up to down there these days?
你这两天总是去那儿做什么？
Apart from chasing our virgins.
除了找我们的姑娘
A couple of Arab ploys that look quite promising.
一些阿拉伯人玩乐看起来也挺有意思
Apart from that, I'm getting quite good at ping-pong.
除此，我乒乓球也玩的不错
阿拉伯人
Arabs.
You can rent one but you can't buy one. Right, Bill?
你租得起却买不起，是吧，比尔？
How's Ricki Tarr these days?
里基•塔尔近来如何？
Fine. We have tea at Fortnum's every afternoon.
挺好的，我们每天在福特纳姆喝下午茶
I require the matter of your discussion with Tarr.
我想知道你与塔尔讨论的话题
I'll tell him. He'll be thrilled.
我会转告他的，他会兴奋的
你耸什么肩？
What's that shrug for?
I'm talking to you about the traitor
我在跟你很严肃的讨论
who cut the throat of our man in Istanbul.
在伊斯坦布尔杀我手下的那个叛徒
I'm talking to you about a defector from your own damn section.
我在跟你讨论从你那个鬼部门出来的叛徒
I'm accusing you of
我要指控你暗地里与敌方间谍有联络
consorting with an enemy agent behind my back.
Don't damn well shrug at me!
别他妈的对我耸肩！
你觉得尝尝班房的日子怎样？
How would you like a term in prison?
Well, I haven't been seeing him.
好吧，我没有见过他
So get your facts straight and get off my back!
有话直说，说完走人
So... if I told you Tarr had recently arrived in Paris,
那么…我若告诉你塔尔最近到巴黎了
你会吃惊么？
would you be surprised?
No, nothing would surprise me about Ricki Tarr.
不会的，里基•塔尔的任何动作都不会令我惊讶
And if I told you we happen to know
那我若告诉你我们偶然发现他的银行账户
多了30000块来路不明的钱
in his bank account last month,
would that surprise you?
你会惊讶吗？
Your man's a defector, Guillam.
你的人出了一个叛徒，吉勒姆
Turned by the opposition
被敌方几个月前收买，如今人家把他派回来了
months ago and now they've sent him back to us.
- What for? - Never mind what for.
- 为什么？ - 不要管为什么
To muddy the water, that's what for.
就是要弄得我们鸡犬不宁
To spread a whole lot of
传播荒谬的言论，让我们白忙活半天
damn nonsense to get us chasing our tails.
关键是
The point is this.
他要回来
He's heading for home.
The first peep from him, you come to the grown-ups.
一看见他就向我们高层汇报
Understood?
明白？
Anyone you see around this table but not another damn soul.
除了在坐的，谁都不许说
Get out.
出去
Peter?
彼得？
Thank you, Belinda.
谢谢你，贝琳达
Oh, Mr. Wu
What shall I do?
Mr. Wu...
All go smoothly, did it?
还顺利吧？
I need to go to the hotel to see George.
我得去旅馆见乔治
Mr. Smiley isn't at the hotel, sir. Change of venue.
史迈利先生不在旅馆，换地方了
George?
乔治？
吉勒姆先生…
Mr. Guillam...
Sorry it took me so long to come home.
很抱歉耽搁那么久才回来
Ricki has been helping us, Peter.
里基一直在帮我们，彼得
他告诉了我们他的所有经历
He's been telling us all about his adventures.
He's a double, George.
他是双重间谍，乔治
There is no mole. Whole thing's been thought up by Moscow.
根本没有“地鼠”，整个事件都是俄国一手策划的
卡拉30000块收买他
为了你我去偷那些文件
I stole that because of you.
我亲自做间谍都是因为他，你知道我的感受吗？
I spied on my own because of him.
Do you know how that makes me feel?
里基…
Ricki...
you said you sent the Circus
你说给“圆场”发电报，提及依瑞娜的情报
a telegram concerning Irina's information.
- That's right. - What was the date?
- 没错   - 什么时候？
He doesn't know because there was no telegram.
他不知道，因为就没发
- The whole thing is a fabrication. - 20th November.
- 整个事情都是他杜撰的   - 11月20日
It must have been 20th November. Evening.
我清楚的记得是11月20日，晚
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre...
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
高层的每个人都笑得肚子痛
She told me Karla...
- 她告诉我卡拉…   - 11月20日…没有了
November 20th is missing.
Someone is covering their tracks, unless of course you think
有人销毁了记录，除非你觉得
that's just a coincidence?
这 是巧合？
那么钱呢？
What about the money?
30,000 isn't so much for Karla to pay if it protects his mole.
用30000块来保护他的“地鼠”，对卡拉来说不算多
I'm afraid someone in the Circus knows all about Mr. Tarr
恐怕“圆场”里有人对塔尔了如指掌
and is doing everything they can to discredit him.
尽其所能去污蔑他
Everything the Circus thinks is gold
“圆场”自认为重要的情报不过是俄国“中心”制造的垃圾
is shit, made in Moscow.
Why didn't you tell me that you had Tarr?
你为什么要对我隐瞒塔尔？
In case I never made it out of the Circus.
怕我万一没从“圆场”活着出来
I should get some rest.
我得休息了
I suppose you've got your reading to do.
我想你又该忙了
Come up.
上来吧
I met him once.
我见过他一次
Karla.
卡拉
在1955年
In '55.
Moscow Centre was in pieces.
俄国的“中心”支离破碎
Purge after purge.
一遍又一遍的清理
Half their agents were jumping ship.
半数的间谍都潜逃了
I travelled around, signing them up.
我四处奔走，把他们拉入阵营
Hundreds of them.
好几百号人
One of them was calling himself Gerstmann.
有一个自称是格斯特曼的人
He was on his way back to Russia
他准备回俄国
and we were pretty sure he was going to be executed.
我们很肯定他回去只有死路一条
飞机要德里停24小时，我用那那仅有的一天
Plane had a 24-hour lay-over at Delhi and that's how long I had
to convince him to come over to us
说服他投靠我们
instead of going home to die.
别傻乎乎的去寻死
There's a little room.
在那个小屋子
I'm sitting here. He's sitting there.
我坐这儿，他坐那儿
The Americans had him tortured.
美国佬对他严刑逼供过
He had no fingernails.
他连指甲都没了
It's incredibly hot.
实在太残忍了
我很累，只想快点结束，然后回家
I'm very tired and all I want
to do is get this over with and get back home.
Things weren't going well with Ann.
又跟安闹别扭
I give him the usual pitch.
我对他来老的那一套
Come to the West and we can give you a comfortable life,
“来西方吧，告诉我们你知道的
after questioning.
“然后我们给你安稳的生活”
What did he say?
他怎么回答？
Think of your wife.
“想想你的妻子
You have a wife, don't you?
“你有妻子，对吧？
“我给你带了点烟
Here. I brought you some cigarettes, by the way.
Use my lighter.
“用我的打火机
We could arrange for her to join you.
“我们可以把她安排到你那儿，我们有很多存货可以交易
We have a lot of stock to trade.
If you go back, she'll be ostracised.
“如果你回去，她会被流放的，想想她
Think of her.
Think about...
“想想吧”…
I kept on...
我一直…
喋喋不休的说他的妻子
...harping on about the damn wife,
telling him more about me than...
把自己的很多事也告诉他…
I should have walked out, of course.
我本该走掉
But for some reason it
但冥冥之中觉得救他很重要，所以我继续
seemed important to save this one, so I go on.
We're not so very different you and I.
“你我都一样
We've both spent our lives
“我们都是花尽毕生
looking for the weaknesses in one another's systems.
“去寻找对方系统中的漏洞
Don't you think it's time to recognise
“你不觉得是时候认清我们的所为
there is as little worth
“对你我双方都毫无意义吗？”
on your side as there is on mine?
Never said a word.
他什么都没说
一个字都没说
Not one word.
次日早晨他回到飞机上
And the next morning he got back on his plane.
他还给我那包烟，没动过
He handed the pack of cigarettes back to me, untouched.
他本是个“烟鬼”，却一根没吸
This was a chain-smoker, mind.
他毅然决然地飞向了死亡
And he flew off to what he presumed would be his death.
他保留了我的打火机
He kept my lighter.
It was a gift.
作为礼物
"To George from Ann.
“安赠予乔治
“倾吾所爱”
All my love.
那是卡拉
That was Karla.
他宁死不屈
He went back to die rather than giving in.
所以，我知道为什么能打败他
Yes, and that's how I know he can be beaten.
因为他太狂热了
Because he's a fanatic.
而狂热常隐藏着一个无人知道的疑问
And the fanatic is always concealing a secret doubt.
他长什么样？
What did he look like?
记不得了
I can't remember.
从今起，彼得
After today, Peter,
你要防着他们的监视
you have to assume they're watching you.
若有什么该收拾的东西
If there's anything you need tidied up,
赶紧收拾
now is the time.
Nearly done.
快完成了
上帝的份上
For God's sake.
有时我觉得他们都一样的白痴
Sometimes I think they're all sharing the same moronic brain.
若有他人，你告诉我
If there's someone else, you can tell me.
我是大人了
I'm a grown-up.
I know. It's just going to be such a wonderful Christmas.
我知道，这将是个美好的圣诞节
抱歉
Excuse me.
And I was too proud to give in.
I had to learn the hard way.
彼得，准备好了
- That pride...  - Peter, when you're ready,
开始播放
put it on now.
Everybody!
大家一起！
- Jerry. - George.
- 杰瑞   - 乔治
- 彼得   - 杰瑞
- Peter. - Jerry.
我得跟你谈谈
I need to talk to you.
About the night Jim Prideaux was killed.
关于吉姆•普里多遇害的那晚
那晚你值班，对吗？
You were duty officer, weren't you?
是的，那晚老总让我守着电话
Yeah. Control asked me to man the phones that night.
He said someone was doing a special job for the service.
他说有人在执行一项特别任务
He wanted someone he could trust.
他要自己信得过的人
出事了，长官
There's been a bit of a panic, sir.
来自外交部的常驻职员
This is from the FO resident clerk.
一则匈牙利简要新闻
A Hungarian news bulletin.
“化名为埃利斯的英国间谍
British spy, work name Ellis,
travelling with false Hungarian papers,
“利用假护照潜入匈牙利
“计划在布达佩斯绑架一名不愿意透露姓名的匈牙利将军
has attempted to kidnap
an unnamed Hungarian General in Budapest.
“据悉，此人已被击毙
He's been shot.
“相关逮捕行动已经展开”
Other arrests imminent.
要我做个简报么？
Can I have a brief, please?
Sir? Do you want me to deny it, sir?
长官，您希望我予以否认吗？
我得回复，长官
I must have a brief, sir.
老总一个字也不跟我说
I couldn't get a word out of Control.
然后我依据协议去找紧急目录
So I followed protocol and went for the emergency list.
你打给我家了
You rang my house.
碰碰运气看您是否从柏林回来了
Just on the off-chance you were back from Berlin.
你说什么了？
What did you say?
- 你好？   - 你好，史迈利夫人
- 'Hello?' - Hello, Mrs. Smiley.
我是杰瑞，局里的杰瑞•韦斯特比
It's Jerry. Jerry Westerby from the office.
出点小状况
Just that there'd been a bit of a crisis.
Ann said you wasn't back yet and that was it.
安说你尚未回来
然后呢
Go on.
都乱套了
All hell broke loose.
Military yelling about Hungarian tanks on the border.
军方说匈牙利的坦克已经在边界上了
老总和部长开始着急了
Lacon and the minister baying at the door.
谢天谢地比尔•海顿出现了
Thank Christ Bill Haydon turned up when he did.
- 海顿先生   - 没空
- Mr. Haydon. - Not now.
海顿先生！
Mr. Haydon!
Out!
出去！
- 告诉我   - 我试着联系你
- Tell me. - I tried to get hold of you.
我从俱乐部了解到了一些内容，告诉我
I got half a story on the ticker tape at my club. Tell me.
吉姆•普里多中枪了
Jim Prideaux's been shot.
接通匈牙利大使馆
Get me the Hungarian embassy.
你转告你的上司们若敢动吉姆•普里多一根毫毛
You tell your masters what will happen
后果自负
if one hair on Jim Prideaux's head is damaged.
让伊斯特哈斯接电话，让他把匈牙利的特工们召回
Get Esterhase on the phone.
Tell him to call in the Hungarian agents.
好的，先生
Yes, sir.
有普里多的新消息吗？先生？
Any more news on him? Sir?
天哪
Oh, God.
赶紧去他的住处，清除所有相关的东西
We need to get down to his flat, clear out anything linked.
海顿在他的俱乐部听到了消息？
Haydon heard the news at his club?
在萨维尔俱乐部
The Savile.
1：30？那时自动收报机已经不工作了
1:30? The ticker-tape wouldn't have been running.
So how did he know?
那他是怎么知道的？
- Jesus, George. - Peter!
- 天啊，乔治   - 彼得！
- 他怎么知道的？   - 不是你所想的
Jesus Christ, Bill Haydon.
- How could he have known? - It's not what you think.
- 那他是怎么知道的？   - 那晚他在我房间
- Then how did he know? - He was at my house that night.
旅途还行吧？
Good flight?
还行
Yes.
挺好的
Pleasant enough.
I was just passing. I thought I'd call in.
我路过，心想拜访一下
安还在睡，但坚持要起来
Ann was in bed. She insisted on getting up.
她说她一会儿下来
She said she'd be down in a minute.
我带来的，画得真差
That's what I'm dropping off. It's an awful daub really.
不过安说喜欢
But Ann expressed a liking.
What's keeping her?
她喜欢哪一点？
继续
Keep going.
快点，小伙子们，跟上
Come on, lads. Keep up.
快点，比尔！
Come on, Bill!
- 戴上眼镜，胖子？   - 是，先生
- Got your specs on, Jumbo? - Yes, sir.
过来
Come here.
Who's that fellow down there?
你看那是谁？
I don't know, sir.
我不认识
Who is he?
他是谁？
Beggar man?
乞丐？
小偷？
Thief?
为什么他不看这边，嗯？
Why doesn't he look this way, hm?
换做是你，肯定会朝这群追着车嬉戏的孩子看的
Wouldn't you if you saw a
bunch of boys flogging a car round a field?
他怎么回事？讨厌我们？
What's the matter with him? Doesn't he like us?
I don't hold with odd-bods hanging around.
我不喜欢奇怪的家伙在旁边
He might steal the Alvis.
他可能要偷阿尔维斯？
- Which is? - The best car in England, sir.
- 阿尔维斯是什么？   - 英国最好的车，先生
好小伙
Good lad.
How were you briefed for the Budapest mission?
你怎么领到布达佩斯任务的？
Control asked me to come to a flat in Kensington.
老总让我去肯辛顿（伦敦地名）的一处公寓
There's a rotten apple, Jim.
有个内鬼，吉姆
我们得找出来
And we have to find it.
你是怎么理解的，吉姆？
What did you make of it, Jim?
老总的说法？
Control's theory?
我觉得有点疯狂
I thought it was madness.
I know that it is one of five men.
我知道是五人之一
你只用告诉我他们的代号
All I want from you is one code name.
阿勒莱恩
Alleline.
“锅匠”
Tinker.
海顿
Haydon.
“裁缝”
Tailor.
布兰德
Bland.
“士兵”
Soldier.
We drop Sailor. It's too close to Tailor.
我们不用“水手”，读音太接近“裁缝”了
“阔佬”又不太合适
And Rich Man doesn't seem to be applicable.
伊斯特哈斯
Esterhase.
“穷人”
Poor Man.
第五个呢？
And the fifth?
Smiley.
史迈利
I thought it was madness.
我觉得太荒唐了
认为你们五人中有一个是叛徒
To think that any one of you could have been a traitor.
Absolute madness.
这不是疯了是什么
但你还是去了
But you still went.
Why?
为什么？
I went because Control asked me to go.
我去是因为老总之言
这叫尽职
It's called doing one's duty.
At the station I met the legman
在车站我遇到了可以带我去见将军的人
supposed to take me to the General.
侍者一定是慌了
The waiter must have panicked.
It was meant to be a simple snatch job.
原本是个简单的任务
They drove me to some military hospital,
他们把我带到一个部队医院
然后把我运上运输机
and then put me on a transport plane.
I could tell by the stars we were heading east.
从星星来判断，我们在往东飞
然后他们拷问我…
Then they worked me for...
我不知道拷问了多久
I don't know how long.
Weeks, maybe months.
几周或者几个月
你跟他们说什么了？
What did you tell them?
Everything.
所有
I held on for as long as I could
我尽可能的坚持，让其他人有时间撤离
to let everyone get the hell out of there.
他们成功了吗？
Did they?
我的匈牙利同伴们得救了吗？
My networks in Hungary,
did they get out?
没有，他们全栽了
No, they were blown.
传闻说你为了免受皮肉之苦而告发了他们
The story is you blew them to save your own skin.
当拷问者被清走后，这个有个矮个子人出现了
After the interrogators had cleared out,
this little fellow turned up.
Looked like a priest.
像神父
对我的逼供才真正开始
That's when they really started on me.
你最后防线是什么？
What was your last line of defence?
The mole.
“地鼠”
老总疯狂的想法
Control's crazy theory.
I was going to bury that so deep
我将它藏在内心最深处，他们挖不出来
they'd never get it out of me.
- 结果却是个笑话   - 为什么？
- Which was a joke. - Why?
Because they already knew.
因为他们早就知道了
他们只是想看看老总的调查进展的有多深
All they wanted to know was
how far Control had got in his investigation.
No, I don't know her.
不，我不认识她
他们没有问起我吗？
Did they ask about me at all?
问过
Yes.
The little fellow did.
小个子人问过
What did he say about me?
他怎么问的？
他有一个打火机
He had this cigarette lighter.
他拿着打火机在我面前不停地晃
He kept flashing it about for me to see it.
Showed me the inscription.
给我看上面的字
To George From Ann.
- “安赠予”…   - “乔治”
"All my love".
“倾吾所爱”
Karla.
是卡拉
安赠予-乔治   倾吾所爱
It was odd.
太奇怪了
They sent me back to England.
他们把我送回英国
Straight to Sarratt for debriefing'.
直接向萨洛特汇报情况
他说在医院汇报情况的期间还有一位来访者
He said when he was being debriefed at the nursery,
he had a visitor.
Who?
谁？
托比•伊斯特哈斯
Toby Esterhase.
He gave him 1,000 pound and an Alvis.
他给了他1000块和一辆阿尔维斯
并让他销声匿迹，永勿回来
Told him he was dead now.
Couldn't come back.
去过安逸的生活，忘掉发生的一切
Had to become a lotus eater,
forget everything that happened.
Control's theory.
忘掉老总的事情
忘掉锅匠，裁缝等
Tinker, Tailor. All of it.
Yes, that's what I thought.
我在想
How on earth did Esterhase hear about Tinker, Tailor?
托比•伊斯特哈斯是怎么得知锅匠，裁缝这档子事的？
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
She told me Karla was very proud of this.
她说卡拉为此颇为自豪
She said everything the Circus thinks is gold
她说，“圆场”自认为重要的情报不过是俄国“中心”制造的垃圾
is shit, made in Moscow.
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”…
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
不，附近有家旅馆，他们有几间闲置室
No, I had a hotel nearby.
They do have some seedy rooms.
依瑞纳告诉我俄国“中心”
Irina kept telling me in Moscow Centre
所有高层的人都笑得肚子疼
everybody on the top floor was laughing themselves sick.
She told me Karla was very proud of this.
她说卡拉以此为乐
She said everything the Circus thinks is gold is shit.
她说，“圆场”自认为重要的情报不过是垃圾
This meeting is not taking place. Is that clear?
会议尚未开始，明白了吗？
Perfectly, Minister.
明白，部长大人
There is a house somewhere in this city
这城市里有间房子
阿勒莱恩等人于此跟“巫术”的伦敦代表碰头
where Alleline and the others
meet Witchcraft's London representative.
我想拉康跟你说的很明了了
I thought Lacon had made it clear to you.
不要插手“巫术”的事
Keep your nose bloody well out of Witchcraft's business.
It's Lacon's advice I'm following.
我听从的是拉康的建议啊
You told me to follow in Control's footsteps.
你让我紧跟老总的脚步的
我可不会考虑那个忠告的，老总留给我们留的烂摊子
I wouldn't consider that sound advice,
given the mess Control left us with.
It has taken Alleline and, if I may say so, myself
花了阿勒莱恩，还有我自己
this long to get us back in the game.
那么久才使“圆场”正常运作
The man Alleline and the others meet is called Polyakov.
阿勒莱恩等人会见的那人叫波利亚科夫
你以为他的角色就是
You believe his role is to bring information
from Witchcraft to you.
从“巫术”取情报给你
其实他真正的角色是从“地鼠”那里接收情报
His real role is to receive information from the mole
to take back to Karla.
然后带回给卡拉
这… 不可能
That, er... That's not possible.
Made possible.
就是那么回事
By you in the house you persuaded the Treasury to pay for.
你还说服财政部给其拨款
Witchcraft's intelligence is genuine. It's been gold.
“巫术”的情报是确凿的，重要至极
很小部分有价值
It's just enough glitter amongst the chicken feed.
Control didn't believe in miracles or in Witchcraft.
老总不相信什么奇迹或者巫术
But you were lazy and greedy
但贪婪又懒惰的你们
and so you hounded him out of the Circus
把他挤出“圆场”，将卡拉引狼入室
and you let Karla in.
You opened negotiations
你们与美国佬协商交换情报
to exchange intelligence with the Americans.
What they tell the Circus, they'll be telling the Kremlin.
美国佬告诉“圆场”的，也会告诉俄国
Witchcraft's information, the "Gold" Karla let you have,
所谓“巫术”情报，不过是卡拉给你的垃圾情报
it wasn't to lure you.
不是在钓你
而是在钓美国佬
It was to lure the Americans.
Now,
现在
do you want to take credit for that?
你还想要好评吗？
What can we do?
我们该怎么做？
我们有一件“地鼠”想要的东西
We have one thing the mole wants.
- If I go to Paris - You'll go.
- 如果我去巴黎…   - 你必须去
如果我去巴黎
If I go to Paris,
我要你保证你会把依瑞纳弄回来
I want your word that you will get Irina back.
我不管你们用谁交易，我不管
I don't care who you have to trade.
And I am out.
我想要个安稳的家，谢谢，我可不想落下你们这样的下场
I want a family, thank you.
I do not want to end up like you lot.
你要把她弄回来
You will get her back.
I'll do my utmost, Ricki.
我尽力，里基
你好，乔治
Oh, hello, George.
Hello.
你好
I want to talk about loyalty, Toby.
跟我谈谈忠诚吧，托比
Control recruited you, didn't he?
老总将你招致麾下，没错吧？
Found you starving in a museum in Vienna.
在维也纳一个博物馆发现饥寒交迫的你
A wanted man.
还被通缉
Saved your life, I heard.
我听说，他救了你的命
And yet when the time came,
但在关键时刻
when it came to picking sides between him and Alleline,
要你在老总和阿勒莱恩之间做选择的时候
you didn't hesitate.
你毫不犹豫选择了阿勒莱恩
That's understandable, perhaps,
可以理解，可能是你的战争经历作祟
with your war experience.
You survived this long, I suppose,
你能活这么久，我想是因为你那风吹两边倒的能力
because of your ability to change sides.
Serve any master.
服侍各种主子
What? What's... What's this about, George?
这是怎么回事，什么状况，乔治？
It's about which master you've been serving, Toby.
关于你投靠哪边的主子，托比
Intelligence has been leaked, Toby.
情报在泄漏，托比
Someone's been taking files from the Circus.
有人在偷“圆场”的内部资料
No, no, no, no. No.
不不不
This is a mistake, a misunderstanding.
这是个误会，误解
Files were delivered to a Russian attache, weren't they?
文件传递给了俄专员，对不对？
是的
Yes.
And, yes, I delivered them.
是的，我传递的
But so did Percy Alleline.
但是珀西•阿勒莱恩也参与了
好狗
Good boy.
Bill Haydon.
比尔•海顿也有
罗伊•布兰德也有份
And so did Roy Bland.
Things aren't always what they seem, George.
眼见不一定为实，乔治
You should know that.
你应该知道
Look, Moscow thinks Polyakov's...
俄方认为波利亚科夫…
...working for them.
在为其效力
Every now and then we give him the odd file to take back to them.
我们时不时的给些没用的文件让他回去交差
Chicken feed, just to keep his bosses happy.
小部分有价值的也只是为了麻痹他的上司
But Polyakov's our Joe.
但波利亚科夫是我们的人
He's a part of a big operation.
- 他是这项大行动的一分子   - “巫术”行动
Operation Witchcraft.
Yes, I know.
我知道
George.
乔治
- Please, I don't deserve this. - Who gave you the message
- 我不该被这样对待   - 谁让你捎信给吉姆•普里多
for Jim Prideaux to forget about Tinker, Tailor?
让其忘掉锅匠，裁缝这档子事的？
- Bland. - To get rid of Connie Sachs?
- 布兰德   - 除掉康妮•萨克斯呢？
- Westerby? - Bland.
- 还有杰瑞•韦斯特比？   - 布兰德
Or Haydon.
或海顿
I don't know. One of them.
我不知道，但一定是他们之一
Or maybe Percy. No.
也可能是珀西
Well, I don't know who.
好吧，我不知道是谁
You're just the messenger.
你只是信使
Running between them all.
在他们之间跑腿
Anything to serve Witchcraft.
把自己卖给了“巫术”
I know all about your secret source.
你知道的我都知道
And I know something you don't.
你不知道的，我也知道
I know who he is.
我知道谁是幕后人
He's Karla.
是卡拉
One of you has been giving Polyakov the crown jewels.
你们中有人给了波利亚科夫很重要的情报
- I did not know. - Are you still a wanted man, Toby?
- 我不知道   - 你还是被通缉的人吧，托比？
Look, George, I didn't know.
- 听着，乔治，我不知道…   - 你站错队了
You picked the wrong side.
No, you've got to believe me.
不，你得相信我
George, please.
乔治，求你
I am loyal.
我很忠诚
I... I am loyal.
我…我也忠诚
Don't... Don't... Don't send me back.
不要…不要把我送回去
求你，乔治
Please, George.
Don't send me back.
不要把我送回去
Give me the address.
给我那个地址
Where do you meet Polyakov?
你们在哪儿与波利亚科夫接头？
Hey, hey! Dog, dog, be quiet!
嘿嘿！狗狗，安静
What is this? Who are you?
这是做什么？你是谁？
- Mrs. McCraig? - Yes.
- 麦克格雷女士？   - 正是
- What are the safety signals? - The air vent.
-安全信号是什么？   - 排气孔
Open and all's well,
打开代表安全，关闭代表不便入内
closed and you're not to enter.
And the microphone?
麦克风呢？
Peter?
彼得？
The boy stood on the burning deck
男孩站在燃烧的甲板上/只有他逃了出来
whence all but he had fled
The flame that lit the battle's wreck
火焰照亮了遍野的残骸/照亮了头顶的天际
shone brightly o'er the dead.
Beautiful and proud he stood
他勇敢且骄傲地昂首挺立/仿佛要控制整个风暴
as born to rule the storm
A creature of heroic blood,
鲜活的生灵/虽然是个孩子，但却骄傲地活着
a proud though child-like form.
The flames rolled on...
火焰翻滚着…
he would not go. Without his father's word
Merci. Au revoir.
Go on.
继续
整个机构都在找你
The whole service is looking for you, Ricki.
- 他们逮住你会活剥了你   - 我求之不得
They'll skin you alive if they find you.
Maybe I want them to find me.
You can go now.
你可以走了，留下书，把钥匙留在机器上
Leave the books where they are
and put the keys in the machines.
No, Ben stays here.
不必，本你留下
Ricki Tarr claims to have
里基•塔尔声明有关系“圆场”安危的重要情报
information vital to the safeguarding of the Circus.
Mr. Smiley?
史迈利先生？
Taxi approaching Circus.
的士快到了“圆场”了
Tinker.
“锅匠”
“裁缝”
Tailor.
Here comes Soldier.
这是“士兵”
Full house.
到齐了
Well, go on then. Read it out loud.
- 大声读出来   - “阿勒莱恩给塔尔的私信
Personal for Tarr from Alleline.
Require clarification before meeting your request.
“满足你的要求前需解释说明
Quote, information vital
“引文，关系‘圆场’安危的重要情报，结束引文…
to safeguarding of the Circus, unquote.
Does not qualify, send further information.
“太笼统，请发送具体情报”
Ah! That's it, Percy, you keep stalling.
就这样，珀西，你继续无视吧
I warn you, Ben.
我警告你，本，我们中间真的有内鬼
We've got some really lousy people in this outfit.
I wouldn't trust a fucking one of them.
我他妈谁都不信
The meeting's over.
会谈结束
They're leaving.
他们在离场
Craddox says I'll be off in a few days.
科拉道克斯说我几天后就走
I keep thinking how much
我还在想自己在莫斯科会有多想念板球
I'm going to miss the cricket in Moscow.
I was rather hoping you
我希望你能帮我打理点事
might do a little light housekeeping for me.
If I can.
尽量
There's a girl.
有个姑娘，给她些钱，好吗？
Give her some money, would you?
And give her a good cover story.
编个故事
If it helps, tell her I love her.
如果能让她好过些，告诉她我爱她
It's all there.
就这么多
还有一个男孩，给他点封口费
And there's a boy, too.
Slip him a few quid to shut him up.
I know the inquisitors' bag of tricks.
我知道审问官们的伎俩，大多是我教的
I taught most of them.
It's just a reaction.
自己被审有点激动
An over-reaction, if you like.
反应过度了点，你可以这么认为
I did have one or two questions.
我的确还有一两个问题
- About Prideaux. - Goddamn it!
- 关于普里多   - 天哪
- I got him back, didn't I? - Yes, yes, you did.
- 我把他救回来的，不是吗？   - 是的
That was good of you.
你办的好事
I am surprised Karla didn't have him shot.
我惊讶的是卡拉没有杀了他
Or do you think he held back,
或者你觉得他收手
out of delicacy towards you?
是因为和你的微妙关系？
Did Prideaux come and see you
普里多在去匈牙利前有没有见过你？
before he left on the Hungarian mission?
Yes, as a matter of fact he did.
事实上，见过
To say what?
说什么了？
To warn you.
警告你
Because he knew deep down
因为他深知
it was you all along.
一直都是你
So did you.
你也是
I had to pick a side, George.
我不得不选一边，乔治
It was an aesthetic choice as much as a moral one.
品味的选择多过于道德的选择
And the West has become so very ugly.
西方变得丑陋无比
Don't you think?
你不觉得吗？
Did Karla ever consider having you take over the Circus?
卡拉有没有考虑过让你接手“圆场”？
I'm not his bloody office boy!
我可不是他那该死的跑腿人！
What are you, then, Bill?
那你以为你是什么，比尔？
I'm someone who's made his mark.
我是个建功立业的人
Is there anything particular
有什么要我转告给安的吗？
you want me to pass on to Ann?
Oh, that was nothing personal, George.
那不是什么私事，乔治，我希望你能理解
I hope you understand that.
Karla said you were good,
卡拉说你是个厉害的角色
the one we had to worry about.
是我们重点防范的对象
But you do have a blind spot.
不过你确实还有一根软肋
He reckoned if I was known to be Ann's lover,
他推测如果我成了安人尽皆知的情人的话
you wouldn't be able to see me straight.
你反而不会那么容易看清我
And he was right.
事实证明他对了
Up to a point.
在一定程度上
I made this for you, sir.
先生，我帮你做了这个
I don't want you hanging around here any more.
我不想再见到你在这无所事事
Keep away from me from now on.
从即刻起，离我远一点
- Go and join the others. - But...
- 去加入其他同学们   - 可是…
Just... just bloody join in, will you?
去…加入他们，行么？
Go and play, damn you!
去玩吧，真该死！
你能去检查下么，杰瑞？
Could you check, Jerry?
感谢收看TLF字幕   TLF中文字幕站 http://tlfsubs.eastgame.org/   微博地址：http://t.sina.com.cn/tlfsubs   博客地址：http://blog.sina.com.cn/tlfbest